<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To the Great Turk and his King at Argiers together with a postscript of George Pattison's taking the Turks and setting them on their own shoar.</title>
            <author>Fox, George, 1624-1691.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1680</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 47 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A40298</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F1956</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R28611</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">10699707</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 10699707</idno>
            <idno type="VID">45513</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A40298)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 45513)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1384:29)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>To the Great Turk and his King at Argiers together with a postscript of George Pattison's taking the Turks and setting them on their own shoar.</title>
                  <author>Fox, George, 1624-1691.</author>
                  <author>Lurting, Thomas. 1632-1713. Of George Pattisons taking the Turks about the 8 month, 1663.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>20 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Ben. Clark,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1680.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Postscript Of George Pattisons taking the Turks about the 8 month, 1663.": p. 15-20. Signed Thomas Lurting.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Mehmed --  IV, --  Sultan of the Turks, 1642-1693.</term>
               <term>Pattison, George.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Apologetic works.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:45513:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:45513:1"/>
            <p>TO THE Great TURK, AND HIS KING AT ARGIERS TOGETHER WITH A Poſtſcript of <hi>George Pattiſon's</hi> ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the <hi>TURKS,</hi> and ſetting them on their own Shoar.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Ben. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lark,</hi> in <hi>George-yard,</hi> in <hi>Lumbard-ſtreet,</hi> 1680.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:45513:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:45513:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO THE Great TURK, And his King, at ARGIERS.</head>
            <p>IN the Name of the great God, and Lord, Creator, and King of all things, in Heaven and Earth, do I write unto you. And I do take <hi>Enoch, Noah, Abraham,</hi> and <hi>Lot,</hi> and <hi>Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> and <hi>Joſeph,</hi> and <hi>Moſes,</hi> and <hi>David,</hi> and all the Prophets of the Great and moſt High, Dreadful and Terrible God, who is a conſuming Fire to the Wicked, and <hi>John,</hi> as you ſay in your <hi>Alcoran, pag.</hi> 30. <hi>chap</hi> 33. I ſay <hi>John,</hi> the Son of <hi>Zachari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah,</hi> that did affirm Chriſt to be the <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> and to be the Word of God, that great, and chaſte, juſt Prophet, and <hi>Mary</hi> the Mother of Jeſus Chriſt, with all his Holy Apoſtles, and your own <hi>Mahomet</hi> that writ your <hi>Alcoran,</hi> to be Witneſs againſt you and ſome of your practiſes that is practiſed amongſt you, at the dreadful day of Judgment of the great God, when you ſhall all give an Account of your Words, Deeds and Actions, and be rewarded; who will reward every man according to his works, whether they be good or evil. For I ſay of a Truth, That the great God and Lord of Heaven and Earth, and all things therein, is no reſpecter of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, but in every Nation, he that fears God, and worketh Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, is accepted of him.</p>
            <p>And now, O great <hi>Turk,</hi> and the King of <hi>Argier,</hi> I have ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing here to preſent before you, And my deſires are, That you may read, hear and fear, the Great and Terrible, Righteous, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and pure God.</p>
            <p>And here as followeth, you may ſee the Impiety and unchaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and the cruelties of ſome of your People at <hi>Argier,</hi> againſt honeſt, chaſte People, that ſerve and fear and worſhip the moſt
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:45513:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>high God, which you have taken Captive, I ſay you have taken their Ships, their Goods, and ſome you keep Slaves, ſome till they have di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and others you have ſold for Slaves, many people of the moſt high God, in ſcorn called <hi>Quakers,</hi> beſides great numbers of other <hi>Engliſh</hi> people, and people of other Nations cruelly Oppreſt, and inhumanely uſed by you.</p>
            <p>Did ever <hi>Mahomet</hi> give you Authority to rob, ſpoil, and take the Goods of them that do you no harm, and keep Captives the bodies of them, and ſell them, or to beat upon the feet, belly, or back, them which are ſo taken, to make them promiſe more mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney for their Ranſoms than they are able; Or to beat upon the feet with one, or two, or three hundred blows, and hang up by the heels, and beat them which you have taken Captives, becauſe they refuſe to lye with your men, as a man lyeth with a Woman: And is it not contrary to your very wild Bulls, Horſes, Rams, and He Goats, and other wild Creatures and bruit Beaſts?</p>
            <p>And is it not declared againſt, by the Mighty and Eternal God, by <hi>Moſes</hi> and all his holy Prophets; who ſaith, It is an Abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to lie with mankind as with Woman kind: and ſuch men as commit theſe Abominations have defiled the Land, and God will ſpue them out. And ſuch Emperours, Kings and Magiſtrates as wink at, and ſuffer ſuch wicked Abominations and Impieties, the great God will bring his Judgments and Vengeance upon them.</p>
            <p>For the Eternal Holy Lord God Almighty ſaith, who is of purer eyes than to behold Iniquity; If any man lyeth with mankind, as he lyeth with Women, both of theſe men have committed Abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination, they ſhall ſurely be both put to Death; their Blood ſhall be upon them, for all ſuch defile Gods Land and Earth; and for ſuch Iniquities will the mighty God viſit your Land: For he is the mighty God, to ſee all your actions, ways and doings, and hears all your words, and ſees all your thoughts; and you can turn your ſelves no way from the eye and face of God, nor from his hearing your words, nor ſeeing your thoughts. Now would you (to wit, the Great <hi>Turk,</hi> and the King of <hi>Argiers,</hi> or any of your Subjects) be ſo ſerved your ſelves, if you ſhould be ſo taken Captive, to be hanged up by the heels, and beaten with two or three hundred ſtripes, becauſe you eſteem Vertue, Piety and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtity,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:45513:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>and not be forced to lye with other men, as you lye with Women, could you undergo ſuch puniſhment as you inflict upon ſome of our Chaſt people, becauſe they will not ſubmit to ſuch abominable impieties, as ſome of your Subjects would force upon them that you have now in Captivity.</p>
            <p>And would you think it were juſt, according to the Law of the great God, and your own <hi>Alcoran,</hi> if you were taken Captive and your Goods ſpoiled, and to be beaten upon the belly, back on feet, to get more mony than you are able to be give, for the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption out of your Captivity; and is not this contrary to the Juſt Law of the great and holy God, and contrary to his Prophets, yea and contrary to <hi>Mahomet,</hi> that gave forth the <hi>Alcoran:</hi> Or did thoſe which took <hi>Lot, Abraham</hi>'s Friend, and his company Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, beat them, becauſe they would not lye with men as with Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men: Or where did ever <hi>David,</hi> or any of the Prophets of God, force any that they had taken Captive, to lye with man as with Woman as you have done.</p>
            <p>And do not you remember, that when ſome of your Men of War took <hi>George Pattiſon</hi> Captive, who was a <hi>Quaker;</hi> and his Ship, and his Men, and after they conquered them again, without hurting of them, and took them Captive, and when they had done, ſet them on the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Shoar without hurting of them, as may be ſeen in the Poſtcript.</p>
            <p>And where did ever any of the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Men of War do ſo to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> or to the <hi>Quakers;</hi> but on the contrary you beat them, to get more mony than they are able to give you, and becauſe they will not lye with your men as they do with Women; and this pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of yours is neither moral nor humane, but worſe than Beaſts; and ſo do contrary to the Law of the great God, in that you do that to others, which you would not have others do unto you. Now <hi>Mahomet</hi> ſaith in your <hi>Alcoran,</hi> chap. 15. pag. 161. <hi>When the Meſſengers of the great Eternal God, were ſent to destroy the Infidels of</hi> Sodom, <hi>which came to</hi> Lot's <hi>Houſe; and the Inhabitants of the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty came to</hi> Lot's <hi>Houſe, to ſee the Meſſengers: And</hi> Lot <hi>ſaid unto them, I beſeech you, defile not your ſelves with my Gueſts: Fear God, and diſhonour not your ſelves, and how, that</hi> Lot <hi>ſaid, behold my two Daughters, take them, and the Inhabitants ſaid, we do not hinder thee to lodg thy Gueſts: and how that the Inhabitants remained confounded
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:45513:4"/>in their Drunkenneſs, and that God overthrew the City, and turned it upſide down, and cauſed it to Rain with Stones and Fire which utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſtroyed it, who were ſo impious: And this ſhall ſerve for an Example to Paſſengers that ſhall ſee thoſe ruines; and for a mark of the Omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tency of God; to them that believe in his Divine Majeſty, that God avenged on them, they may ſerve for Examples to Poſterity.</hi> Now how can you look up to the great God of Truth, and in your own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Alcoran</hi> and Scriptures concerning <hi>Lot,</hi> and ſuffer ſuch impious abominable Actions, to be committed at <hi>Argier,</hi> for your men to whip young men, and force, becauſe they will not lye with men as women; Is not this as bad or worſe than the <hi>Sodomites,</hi> that would have layn with the Meſſengers that came to <hi>Lots</hi> Houſe, as with Women; who called to <hi>Lot,</hi> and ſaid, bring them out that we may know them, and <hi>Lot</hi> proffered them his two Daughters to ſave the Meſſengers. And is not the Eternal God, that changes not the ſame, to Judge and Deſtroy them that act ſuch things among you, as them in <hi>Sodom</hi> did, and that ſuffer ſuch Impieties and Abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations to be acted, and love their Sins more than Piety.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Mahomet</hi> ſaith in your <hi>Alcoran,</hi> Chap. 15. <hi>God guideth not the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>njuſt.</hi> and therefore the Great and Eternal God doth not guide your people in theſe Impieties; and you ſay, The greateſt part of the World are impious, becauſe of the enormities of their Crimes; But now look among your own Subjects, and ſee if they be not the ſame for crimes, impieties, and enormities. And if <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus</hi> the Son of <hi>Mary,</hi> who confirms the antient Scriptures be full of Light, and of the Goſpel, to conduct the people the right way, with a confirmation of the Old Teſtament, and guide, and inſtruct for the righteous, then certain your actions before mentioned at <hi>Argier,</hi> and that way, doth declare you not to be in this right way of Light, and Goſpel of Jeſus.</p>
            <p>And again <hi>Mahomet</hi> ſaith in your <hi>Alcoran, ſuch as ſhall not Judge conformable to the Laws of God, are unjust:</hi> and theſe Abominable Impieties of yours, are not conformable to the Law of God, but leads you into the way of Deſtruction, from the way of Salvation, and therefore unjuſt.</p>
            <p>And you ſay in your <hi>Alcoran,</hi> chap. 5. <hi>God loveth the Juſt,</hi> but he hateth ſuch unjuſt action of yours: And in your <hi>Alcoran</hi> you write, <hi>That God puniſhed the Children of</hi> Iſrael <hi>that polluted the earth, and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:45513:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>oppoſed the Will of God,</hi> &amp;c. and further you ſay, <hi>He that ſlayeth an Innocent perſon, ſhall be puniſhed as if he had ſlain the whole World; and he that ſhall give his life ſhall be recompenſed as if he had given Life to the whole World.</hi> Now hath not your practiſe herein been contrary to your <hi>Alcoran,</hi> as in chap. 5. and pag. 64.65.</p>
            <p>And do not you ſay, <hi>you gave them your Curſe, that alter'd the words of the Scripture,</hi> and alſo ſaith, <hi>That God loves them that do good,</hi> c. 5 p. 65.</p>
            <p>Now theſe bad actions of yours are contrary to the Scriptures, and contrary to your <hi>Alcoran,</hi> and therefore how can God love you. And again you ſay, <hi>Such as have the Knowledg of the Scriptures, ought to believe in Jeſus before their Death; for he ſhall be a Witneſs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them of their Actions in the day of Judgement.</hi> Now ye <hi>Turks</hi> conſider how you do acknowledge the Scriptures, and believe in Jeſus, and in God, who ſheweth forth ſuch abominable Actions: and do not you think that Jeſus the Meſſiah, will be a Witneſs againſt you at the day of Judgement, for your impitles and your infidelity, and muſt not all ſuch be caſt into the loweſt Hell, and find no relief except they repent in their life-time, and do good Works meet for Repentance, and reſign your ſelves to God, and obey his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments; as to this effect you ſay in your <hi>Alcoran,</hi> cap. 4. pag. 61.</p>
            <p>And you confeſs, <hi>That every man ſhall taſte Death, and have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward at the day of Judgement.</hi> And do you think of the day of Judgement, and fear God, that do ſuch Evils and Impieties.</p>
            <p>And again, you ſay in the <hi>Alcoran, That you would have the fear of God before your eyes, and if you be converted, your Principle remains unto you, do injuſtice to no man, then it ſhall not be done unto you: if your Debtors be not able to pay and in want, you do well to ſtay their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniency,</hi> chap. 2. page 28.</p>
            <p>Now do not you <hi>Turks</hi> ſhew, That you are degenerated from your Principle, and are not converted, that do theſe unjuſt, abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable things to others, that you would not have them do unto you, and beat your Slaves and Captives, becauſe they will not give you more mony than they have to redeem themſelves with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, and becauſe they will not lye with your men as with Women; and therefore, as you ſay in the ſame Chapter, <hi>The Wicked ſhall be deprived of Protection at the day of Judgement.</hi> And again in your <hi>Alcoran</hi> you ſay, <hi>You ſhall all one day appear before his Divine Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, to be judged.</hi> Therefore dread and fear this day, you that
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:45513:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>commit ſuch Abominations, and act ſuch Cruelties. Again, <hi>Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met</hi> ſaith, in <hi>c.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 19. <hi>There be men whoſe Speeches may be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to thee in this World, they wiil call God to witneſs what is in their hearts, nevertheleſs, they are very pernicious.</hi> Now, is not this your Condition at <hi>Argier?</hi> And you ſay, God knoweth, he is with them that fear him, <hi>c.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 18. But truly you do ſhew that you are not in this fear, <hi>c.</hi> &amp; <hi>p.</hi> 11. Again, you ſay, <hi>Whereſoever men do turn themſelves, there the Face of God will meet them, his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity extendeth through the whole Earth.</hi> Therefore how dare you in the face and ſight of God act ſuch things, and not repent, and fear his divine Majeſty: And therefore take heed that you do not purchaſe to your ſelves the Life and Luſts of the World, and quit Paradice, and go into miſery; as you ſay in your 8 <hi>page.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And again, <hi>Mahomet</hi> ſaith, <hi>If Slaves have recourſe to you, ye ſhall redeem them,</hi> &amp;c. page 8. Now you are far from redeeming Slaves, when you beat them for not giving you Mony according to your wills, and more than they can give, and alſo beat them, becauſe they will not commit horrid Uncleanneſs, to defile and abuſe their Bodies with Mankind. And you ſay that <hi>Adam</hi> beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged pardon for his Fault, who departed from his Grace, and have not you need of this, and repent and turn to the Lord, you who defiles the Earth? For elſe is not Hell prepared for all ſuch that po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutes the Earth, for you are not obſervers of Gods Law, nor of your own <hi>Alcoran,</hi> as you may ſee, <hi>chap.</hi> 2. <hi>page</hi> 2.</p>
            <p>And the great God, the Creator of all, doth know all in Heaven and in Earth, both what is done in ſecret and openly, and all is naked before him, who will reward every man according to his Works; He is a conſuming Fire.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Mahomet</hi> ſaith, <hi>that God guideth not the Wicked,</hi> chap. 19. page 115. And again, he ſaith, <hi>Alms is appointed for the Poor, for them that recommend themſelves to God, to redeem Slaves, and ſuch as are in Debt,</hi> in the ſame chap. p. 11. I ſay then, according to your own <hi>Alcoran,</hi> God hath not been your Guide, to be ſo wicked againſt the Slaves you take: And as for your Alms, and Charity to them, is manifeſt but cold: But where did any called Chriſtians, after they had taken any of you <hi>Turks,</hi> beat you, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe you would not give them more mony than you had, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe you would not lie with Men as with Women: And if God be
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:45513:5"/>full of goodneſs for the people, as <hi>Mahomet</hi> ſaith, <hi>c.</hi> 10. <hi>p.</hi> 130. then you are degenerated from his Goodneſs.</p>
            <p>And again, in <hi>c.</hi> 11. <hi>p.</hi> 134. <hi>Mahomet</hi> ſaith, That <hi>God ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward every one according to his Works;</hi> And therefore, why do not you dread and fear this great God of Heaven and Earth? And <hi>c.</hi> 11. <hi>p.</hi> 140. <hi>Mahomet</hi> ſaith, detain nothing from your Neighbours, defile not the Earth, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Then how can you detain mens Children, and Servants, and Goods from them, and beat them, becauſe they will not give you more Mony than they have, to redeem them, and hang them up by the heels and beat them, becauſe they will not lie with Men, as with Women; O horrible Impieties; And did not God deſtroy ſuch both in the day of <hi>Noah, Abraham, Lot,</hi> and <hi>Moſes,</hi> that did corrupt and defile the Earth?</p>
            <p>And, <hi>c.</hi> 12. <hi>p.</hi> 144. <hi>How</hi> Joſeph's <hi>Mistreſs would have had him to have been unchaſt, and how amorous ſhe was of</hi> Joſeph <hi>her Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band's Slave, and how that</hi> Joſeph <hi>ſaid, O God, I had rather be a Priſoner, than do what ſhe deſireth.</hi> Now here, Do not you act contrary to <hi>Joſeph</hi> and your own <hi>Alcoran</hi> who would force your Captives to lie with you as with Women? Is not this worſe then <hi>Joſeph</hi>'s Miſtreſs, who would not only force, but beat them with ſome hundreds of Stripes, becauſe they will not ſubmit to your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>humane Impieties, and unchaſte wicked Luſts? For our Friends, that are your Captives, are of <hi>Joſeph</hi>'s Spirit, that obey the Law of the moſt high God. And, you ſay, that <hi>Joſeph's Miſtreſs did con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs he was a juſt man, but</hi> Joſeph <hi>would not be a Traytor to his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter;</hi> No more can the People of God called <hi>Quakers,</hi> your Slaves in <hi>Argier,</hi> be Traytors to God, and diſobey his juſt Laws, that condemns ſuch unchaſte inhumane Impieties, that you <hi>Turks</hi> would force in <hi>Argier,</hi> to lie with Men as with Women, they had rather be Priſoners all the days of their Lives.</p>
            <p>And therefore, as <hi>Mahomet</hi> ſaith, <hi>c.</hi> 19. <hi>p.</hi> 188 <hi>That all ſuch Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels, for Actions.</hi> For, as you confeſs, <hi>You must all appear before the Lord, at the Day of Judgment, and give an account of your actions.</hi> And could the old World, and <hi>Sodom,</hi> be more vicious than you, that do ſuch wicked Actions. And <hi>Mahomet</hi> ſaith, chap. 21. pag. 200. That <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Salomon who rendred Juſtice in the Field, that the Flocks of the Village entred by night without Shephards;</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:45513:6"/>Now are not you fallen and degenerated from this Juſtice both of <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Solomon?</hi> that the Flocks cannot enter the Villages with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Shepherds and Guides, let the Great God of Truth judge; And therefore what will you ſay in the day of Judgement, when the Prophets and your own <hi>Alcoran</hi> will be againſt you; for will not you that act ſuch things, be found Fire-brands of Hell; and how can ſuch expect the Lords Protection: and therefore the great God will call you to an account for all your actions; and all men upon the earth, who tranſgreſs his good and holy Juſt Law: and if the God of Truth be King of the whole Earth, as you confeſs in your <hi>Alcoran</hi> chap. 23. pag. 212: <hi>and the Creator of all, and King of all things, both in Heaven and Earth,</hi> then how dare you act ſuch unchaſt, unjuſt things, and be ſuch Wicked Rebels againſt his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment and Juſt Law, and therefore the Ballance of the Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, as you confeſs, ſhall be light of good Works, that obeys not the Commandments of God.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Mahomet</hi> ſaith chap. 29. page 245. <hi>how God delivered</hi> Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham <hi>from the People that would have killed him:</hi> but if you were in the ſteps and Faith of <hi>Abraham</hi> or <hi>Lot,</hi> you would not defile your ſelves with filthineſs; and do not you confeſs, That <hi>Lot</hi> ſaid to them of <hi>Sodom,</hi> ye defile your ſelves with filthineſs, unknown to any before you, and told them they inclined to the love of men; ye rob in the high-ways and defile one another: Now have not you <hi>Turks</hi> forgotten <hi>Lots</hi> Preaching, and degenerated from your own <hi>Alcoran,</hi> and are become Robbers, and to follow that unknown fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſs, with which you defile your ſelves (to wit,) the Luſt of men: that you beat thoſe men which you have robb'd and ſpoyl'd, and taken Captive, becauſe they will not lye with your men as Women: And therefore how can you expect, but that Gods Wrath and Indignation will fall upon you for your impieties, and you to be ſet forth for examples to Poſterity, whom the Devil hath ſedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced from the right way of the Lord, and of his righteous law, who neither follows your own <hi>Mahomet,</hi> what he hath declared, but the vanities of Infidelity and fears not God, his Divine Majeſty, nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard his Law, but have contemned his Commandments. And therefore <hi>Mahomet</hi> ſaith chap. 51. pag. 326. <hi>ſuch as fear not God, and do not believe, ſhall be puniſhed in Hell fire.</hi> And again <hi>Mahomet</hi> ſaith, chap. 59. pag. 344. <hi>In the Name of God, gracious and merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:45513:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>whatſoever is in Heaven and Earth exalts the Glory of God, he is Omnipotent and Wiſe; It is he that exiles the Wicked from among them that knoweth his Law:</hi> Then here are not you the Wicked that are exiled, that diſobey his Law, and commit ſuch abominable things, and therefore you cannot exalt Gods Glory, neither are you gracious nor merciful, that do thus beat and abuſe your Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives, becauſe they will not lye with men as Women, yea 2 or 300 Stripes, and to give more mony for their Redemption than they are able to give: and therefore ſuch Wickedneſs as yours doth diſhonour the great God, and you will be made the examples of his Wrath, and ſuffer the pains of Hell fire, except ye repent; as <hi>Mahomet</hi> ſaith chap. 67. pag. 356.</p>
            <p>And therefore, do not ſtreng then your ſelves in Impiety, nor put your Fingers in your Ears and ſtop them, and cover your Head with your Garments, that you will neither hear nor ſee Gods Law, as <hi>Mahomet</hi> tells you, which reproves you for your Impieties, who are erred from the right way of the Lord, that do commit ſuch things. And <hi>c.</hi> 93. <hi>p.</hi> 385. <hi>Mahomet</hi> tells you, how the Lord inriches you, and that you ſhould do no injury to the Orphans, and that you ſhould not devour the poor, but that you ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count the Graces that God hath conferred upon you: Now, are not you <hi>Turks</hi> degenerated, not only from the Law of God, but from <hi>Mahomet</hi>'s teaching in his <hi>Alcoran?</hi> Do not ye devour the poor Orphans, who you take Captive, and injure them when you beat them, becauſe they will not give you more mony than they have, and becauſe they will not lie with your men, which is abominable?</p>
            <p>Again, <hi>Mahomet</hi> ſaith, <hi>c.</hi> 102. <hi>p.</hi> 319. <hi>He that perſecutes his Neighbour, miſery is upon him, and perſecution ſhall come upon him, and conquer him;</hi> And therefore, if ye believe his <hi>Alcoran,</hi> this will be fulfilled unto you, that do ſuch things. And again, <hi>Mahomet</hi> ſaith, <hi>He that heaps up Treaſures, and is buſie to count them, thinks they will make him Immortal,</hi> he tells ſuch what ſhall be their miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, <hi>that their Hearts ſhall burn in the fire of Hell:</hi> and therefore what will become of you, who get your Treaſure by Theft and Robbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and taking Captives, and beat them to give more mony for Redemption than they have, neither do not think you any harm, who are the Subjects of the great God, and keep his Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments;
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:45513:7"/>ſurely ſuch that do ſo, will be overwhelmed with the Flames of Hell, and bound to great Pillars of the ſame. And again <hi>Mahomet</hi> ſaith, chap 105. pag. 391. <hi>He that devours the Subſtance of Orphans, and the Bread of the Poor, Blaſphemes againſt the Law of God, and miſery is upon him.</hi> Now are not you men of <hi>Argier,</hi> that devours the ſubſtance of Orphans, and hinder men to do well and follow their lawful buſineſs: and ſo are not only un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Judgement of the Law of God, but under the Judgement of your <hi>Mahoment,</hi> who live there by ſpoyling and robbing your Neighbour, that think you no hurt.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Jeſus</hi> the Son of <hi>Mary,</hi> which you confeſs in your <hi>Alcoran</hi> was ſent to guide and inſtruct people in the right way, whom you confeſs was a great Prophet, and do find fault with the <hi>Jews</hi> becauſe they did not obey him, he commands people that they ſhould love their enemies, and do good unto enemies, and pray for enemies, and do good unto them that deſpightfully uſe them. And you ſay in your <hi>Alcoran, That Jeſus ſhall be a Witneſs in the day of Judgement, against ſuch as obey not his Law;</hi> then do not you believe he will be a Witneſs againſt you, for diſobeying his Command and Law, who hate not only them you think your enemies, but thoſe that neither think nor do you harm, and take them Captive, and rob and ſpoil them of their Goods; and beat them becauſe they will not be defiled with your men, and give you more mony for their Ranſom than they are able to give.</p>
            <p>And again <hi>Mahomet</hi> ſaith, chap. 3. pag. 34 <hi>That</hi> Jeſus <hi>ſaid, Who ſhall ſuſtain the Law of God in my abſence? and the Apoſtles anſwered him, We will ſustain the Law of God in thy abſence,</hi> &amp;c. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore why do not you believe in the Law of God, according to Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus and the Prophets; for Jeſus Apoſtles declared againſt ſuch men as burned in their Luſts one towards another, men with men; and who knew the Judgements of God was upon them that committed. ſuch things, and that they were worthy of Death, and yet did not only do ſuch things, but had pleaſure in them that did them; and therefore you <hi>Turks</hi> that do ſuch things, are Judged by the great God, and all his Holy Prophets, and Jeſus Chriſt, and his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, to Act contrary to Gods pure, juſt, holy, righteous Law, and they are Witneſſes againſt you, as is alſo your own <hi>Alcoran.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now, conſider O ye <hi>Turks,</hi> The great and holy Eternal God,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:45513:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>who made the World and all things therein, he is Lord of Heaven and Earth, and great King over all, and dwelleth not in Temples made with hands, but in Temples of Peoples hearts, neither is he Worſhipped with mens hands; he giveth to all breath, life, and all things, that they might ſerve and worſhip him, and he hath made of one Bloud all Nations of men, for to dwell on the face of the Earth; and hath determined the times before appointed, and the bounds of their Habitations, and all ſhould ſeek after the Lord, who fills Heaven and Earth, who is not far from any people, and now commands all men every where to repent; becauſe he hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed a day in which he will Judge the World in Righteouſneſs; And therefore how can you do any Violence againſt your own fleſh and bloud, ſeeing that God hath made of one Bloud all Nations of men, and commands you to do unto all men, as you would have them do unto you, yea and to love one another, and to love ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies: and therefore it is the Devil that ſeduces you, and makes you hate both your Friends and Enemies, and your own Fleſh and Bloud. And alſo the Eternal God of Truth commands, That Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and Supplications be made for all men, who would have all men to be ſaved, and come to the knowledge of the Truth, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you ought not to deſtroy them, nor to hurt them, which you cannot hurt, if you truly pray for them: For the Lord hath commanded his Prophet <hi>Ezekiel</hi> to ſay unto the People, <hi>As I live ſaith the Lord, I have no pleaſure in the Death of the Wicked, but that the Wicked turn from his Wicked ways and live: Therefore turn ye, turn ye from your evil ways, for why will ye Die, for I have no pleaſure in the Death of him that Dieth, ſaith the Lord God of Truth, therefore turn your ſelves to the Lord and ye ſhall live; for the Lord God that Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Heavens and the Earth, and ſtretched them out; he that ſpread forth the Earth, and that which comes out of it, he that giveth breath to the People upon it, and Spirit to them that walk therein, his Law and Covenant, and Light is to be minded and kept that he hath given to the Nations, ſo that every one that hath Breath, may praiſe the Lord in his Covenant of light; for in the hand of the Lord is the Soul of eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry living thing, and the Breath of all mankind. And the Lord opens unto them that obey him, his good Treaſure; that they have the Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings from above and alſo from below; and he is the Lord God of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of all fleſh, and therefore all are to worſhip and ſerve him in the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:45513:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>Spirit and Truth, who is the Lord God of their Spirits: And he was the Teacher of</hi> Adam <hi>and</hi> Eve, <hi>and as long as they kept under his Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings they were happy; but when they forſook Gods Teaching, and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed the Devils and Sathans Teaching, who led them from God into corruptions, filthineſs, uncleanneſs, and into Diviſions, and to deſtroy one another, but according to Gods Promiſes and Prophets, the Seed of the Woman is come to bruiſe the Serpents head: and is the Speaker and Teacher again to his People by it, as he was to</hi> Adam <hi>and</hi> Eve <hi>in Paradice; Glory and Praiſe to the Great and Eternal God for Ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And God by his Prophets ſaid, <hi>That he would pour out of his Spirit upon all Fleſh:</hi> And Jeſus Chriſt ſaid, <hi>That God was a Spirit, and they that Worſhip him, muſt Worſhip him in Spirit and Truth:</hi> And now all Men and Women in the whole World, they muſt come to the Spirit and the Truth in their own hearts, which they have from the God of Truth, if they do ſerve and worſhip the holy and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal God of Truth, in his Spirit and Truth: and theſe are the true Worſhippers that Worſhip the Eternal God of Truth in his Spirit and Truth, which the Devil, which is the foul corrupt Spirit is out of, who abode not in the Truth, and there is no Truth in him, therefore he is not to be followed nor worſhipped, but the God of Truth: and the Grace of God which brings Salvation, hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared to all men, which teacheth us his people to deny Ungodli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Worldly Luſts, we living Soberly, Righteouſly and Godly in this preſent World: Now all men muſt come to this Grace of God in their hearts, which appears to them in their hearts, which ſhews them their Ungodlineſs and Worldly Luſts, and their unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, and it will teach them to forſake it, and bring their Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation; but if that you do turn this Grace of God into wantonneſs, and walk deſpightfully againſt the Spirit of Grace, you walk in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpight of that which ſhould bring your Salvation, then you bring the Wrath and Indignation of the great God againſt you, who a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe his Grace and Favour; and the Meſſiah and you and <hi>Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met</hi> do conſeſs that <hi>John</hi> declares Chriſt the Meſſiah to be the Word, then you are to obey him. Moreover <hi>John</hi> ſaith, That he was not that Light, but ſent to bear Witneſs of that Light, <hi>and that was the true Light which lighteth every man that cometh into the World:</hi> Now you all being enlightened with this true Light, which Light lets you ſee all your evil deeds and actions that you do, and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:45513:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>all your evil words and thoughts that you ſpeak and think. And every one of you that doth Truth cometh to the Light, that your Deeds may be manifeſt they are wrought in God, from whom they have this Light in whom there is no Darkneſs; but every one of you that doth evil hateth the light, then you hate Jeſus Chriſt and the Eternal God, neither will you come to the light, leſt your Deeds ſhould be reproved by the light; and this is the Condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>That Light is come into the World, and men love Darkneſs rather than Light, becauſe their Deeds be Evil.</hi> Now if you would do the Truth and come to the Light and love it, it ſhines in your hearts, and would give you the Light of the knowledge of the Glory of God, in the face of Jeſus Chriſt, and then you would know this Heavenly Treaſure in your Earthen Veſſels, and the excellency of this power to be of God, and not of your ſelves. And you do con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, That Jeſus Chriſt was not begotten by the Will of man, who was Conceived of <hi>Mary,</hi> and that ſhe ſhould Conceive and bring forth without the touching of man, and he being Conceived by the Holy Spirit, then whoſe Son can he be but Gods; who taught him the Scriptures, and the myſteryes of the Laws of the Old Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, and the Goſpel; who was a Prophet to the Children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> as you confeſs in your <hi>Alcoran,</hi> chap. 3. pag. 34. <hi>So he was declared to be Gods Son in the power. according to the Spirit of Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs by the Reſurrection from the Dead; for all Died in</hi> Adam, <hi>and he taſted Death for every man, and is riſen for the Juſt fication of all that believe in him, the true Light of the Eternal God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now all ye <hi>Turks,</hi> and all People upon the earth; God who is Immortal, Eternal, and Inviſible, he has poured out of his Spirit upon you all; but if you do grieve it, and vex, and rebel, and err from and againſt his good Spirit, then you go from Gods Law, and that which doth Witneſs for him, which is, his Spirit in your hearts, which is a Witneſs for the King of Kings, yea, the great King of Heaven and Earth; I ſay, this Witneſs doth Witneſs for the great God, who will Judge the World in Righteouſneſs, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to this Witneſs, and the Secrets of every mans heart, he by his Spirit doth ſhew unto man his Thoughts and the Imaginations of his heart, and ſearches the Heart, and tryes the Reins, and all things are naked and open to him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> who is a Conſuming Fire to the Wicked: Now this Spirit of the God of Truth, which he hath pou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:45513:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>upon all fleſh of men and women, it is a Witneſs againſt you for the pure God, for all your unrighteous, and ungodly, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious actions, and your bad Thoughts and Words, and whatever you do or act that is unjuſt, and unholy, and for what you do to others, you would not have done to you; the Holy Spirit of the great God of Truth is a Witneſs againſt you: It was a Witneſs againſt <hi>Adam</hi> and the Old World that diſobeyed him; it was a Witneſs againſt the <hi>Jews;</hi> and it is a Witneſs againſt all Chriſtians that walk not in it; and <hi>Turks,</hi> and all people upon the earth: and they that are led by the good Spirit of God, are his Children, Sons and Daughters: and therefore prize your time while you have it, ye <hi>Turks</hi> and others, and mind Gods good Spirit, and his Light and Grace: which will bring your Salvation, that you may come into favour with the God of Truth.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>From him whoſe Love is to God and Jeſus Chriſt, the Juſt and Holy One, and all his Holy Prophets and Apostles, and all People upon the Earth, for their Salvation, and deſires their Eternal Good and Happineſs, and not any mans Deſtruction. G. Fox.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Kingſton</hi> upon <hi>Thames,</hi> 
                  <date>the 16 of the fifth month, 1680.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:45513:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
            <head>Of George <hi>Pattiſons</hi> taking the <hi>Turks</hi> about the <hi>8</hi> Month <hi>1663.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Dear Friend,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THine I have received: In Anſwer to thy requeſt, I have given thee an Account as well and as near as I can; but as to the exact time I cannot, for I have not my Books. I was <hi>George Pattiſons</hi> Mate, and coming from <hi>Venice,</hi> being near a <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Iſland called <hi>May-York,</hi> we were Chaſed by a <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Ship or <hi>Patah,</hi> as ſometimes before we had been, and thinking by our Veſſels well Sailing, might eſcape: But Providence Ordered it ſo, That by carrying over-much Sail, ſome of our Materials gave way, by which means the ſaid <hi>Turk</hi> came up with us, and commanded the Maſter on Board, who accordingly went with four men more, leaving me and three men and a boy on board our Ship; and ſo ſoon as our men came on Board the <hi>Turk,</hi> they took them all out of the Boat, and came about 14 <hi>Turks</hi> in our Boat. All which time I was under a very great Exerciſe in Spirit, not ſo much for my ſelf, becauſe I had a ſecret hope of relief; but a great ſtreſs lay upon me for the men in this very Juncture of time; for all hope of outward appearance being then gone; the Maſter being on board of the <hi>Turk,</hi> and four more, and the <hi>Turks</hi> juſt coming on Board, I being as one, even as if I were or were not, only deſiring of the Lord for pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in ſuch an Exerciſe, and going to the Veſſel ſide, to ſee the <hi>Turks</hi> come in, the Word of Life run through me, <hi>Be not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid, for all this thou ſhalt not go to</hi> Argier. And I having for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:45513:10"/>good experience of the Lords doing upon ſeveral ſuch like occaſions, as in times of War I believed what the Lord did ſay in me: At this all kind of fear was taken from me, and I received them as a man might his Friend; and they were as Civil, ſo ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them all parts of the Veſſel, and what ſhe was laden withal, then I ſaid to them that were our men; Be not afraid, for I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve for all this we ſhall not go to <hi>Argier,</hi> but let me deſire you, as you have been willing to obey me, ſo be as willing to obey the <hi>Turks.</hi> For by our ſo doing I ſaw we got over them, for when they ſaw our great diligence, it made them careleſs of us, I mean, in ſecuring of us: So when they had taken ſome ſmall matter of what we were laden withal, ſome went on Board their own Ship a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, and ſome ſtaid with us, which were about eight: Then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan I to think of the Maſter and the other four, which were in the <hi>Turks</hi> Ship; for as for my ſelf and the other with me, I had no fear at all; Nay, I was ſo far from it, That I ſaid to one then, <hi>Were but the Master on Board, and the reſt, if there were twice ſo many</hi> Turks <hi>I ſhould not fear them:</hi> So my earneſt deſire was to the Lord, That he would put it into their hearts to ſend him on board with the reſt, and good was the Lord in anſwering, for it was as a Seal to what he before ſpoke through me.</p>
            <p>As ſoon as the Maſter was on Board with the reſt, all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of fear was off on me as to my going to <hi>Argier,</hi> and ſome ſaid to me, I was a ſtrange man, I was afraid before I was taken, but now I was taken I was not; my Anſwer was, I now believe I ſhall not go to <hi>Argier,</hi> and if you will be ruled by me, I will act for your delivery as well as my own. But as yet I ſaw no way made, for they were all Arm'd, and we without Arms. Now we being altogether, except the Maſter, I began to reaſon with them, What if we ſhould overcome the <hi>Turks</hi> and go to <hi>May York?</hi> At which they very much rejoyced; and one ſaid, I will kill one or two; another ſaid, I will cut as many of their Throats as you will have me; this was our mens Anſwer. At which I was much troubled, and ſaid unto them, If I knew any of them that offered to touch a <hi>Turk,</hi> I would tell the <hi>Turks</hi> my ſelf. But ſaid to them? If you will be rul'd, I will act for you, if not, I will be ſtill; to which they agreed to do what I would have them. Then ſaid I, if the <hi>Turks</hi> bid you do any thing, do
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:45513:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>it without grumbling, and with as much diligence and quickneſs as you can, for I ſee that pleaſes them, and that will cauſe them to let us be together: To which they agreed.</p>
            <p>Then I went to the Maſter, who was a man of a very bold Spirit, and told him our Intents; whoſe Anſwer to me was, If we offered to riſe, and they overcame us, we had as good be burnt alive, the which I knew very well. But I could get him no way to adhere to me, in that he being fearful of Blood-ſhed; for that was his reaſon: Inſomuch that at laſt I told him we were reſolved, and I queſtioned not to do it without one drop of Blood ſpilt, and I believed that the Lord would proſper it, by reaſon I could rather go to <hi>Argier</hi> than to kill a <hi>Turk:</hi> So at laſt he agreed to this, to let me do what I would, Provided we killed none: at that time there being ſtill two <hi>Turks</hi> lying in the Cabin with him; So that he was to lie in the Cabin, that by his being there they ſhould miſtruſt nothing, which accordingly he did. And having bad Weather, and loſt the Company of the Man of War; the <hi>Turks</hi> ſeeing our diligence, made them care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs of us.</p>
            <p>So the ſecond night, after the Captain was gone to ſleep, I perſwaded one to lye in my Cabin, and ſo one in another, till at laſt it raining very much, I perſwaded them all down to ſleep; and when aſleep got their Arms in Poſſeſſion. Then ſaid I to the men of our Veſſel: Now have we the <hi>Turks</hi> at our Command; no man ſhall hurt any of them, for if you do, I will be againſt you: But this we will do, now they are under we will keep them ſo, and go to <hi>May-York.</hi> So when I had ordered ſome to keep the Doors, if any ſhould come out, ſtraightly charging the ſpilling of no Blood; and ſo altered our Courſe for <hi>May York,</hi> the which in the Morning we were fair by: So my Order was to our men, if any offer'd to come out, not to let out above one at a time. And in the morning one came out, expecting to have ſeen their own Country, but on the contrary it was <hi>May-York.</hi> Now, ſaid I to our men, be careful of the Door, for when he goes in, we ſhall ſee what they will do. And as ſoon as he told them we were going towards <hi>May York,</hi> they inſtead of riſing fell all to crying, for their hearts were taken from them. So they deſired they might not be ſold; the which I promiſed
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:45513:11"/>they ſhould not. So ſoon as I had pacified them, then I went in to the Maſter, he not yet knowing what was done, and ſo he told their Captain what we had done, how that we had over-come his men, and that we were going for <hi>May York.</hi> At which unexpected News he Wept, and deſired the Maſter not to ſell him; the which he promiſed he would not. Then we told the Captain we would make a place to hide them in, where the <hi>Spaniards</hi> ſhould not find them; at which they were very glad, and we did accordingly. So when we came in, the Maſter went on Shoar with four more, and left me on board with the <hi>Turks</hi> which were ten. And when he had done his buſineſs, not taking Product, leſt the <hi>Spaniards</hi> ſhould come and ſee the <hi>Turks</hi>—. But at Night an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Maſter came on Board, being an Acquaintance; and after ſome Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, we told him if he would not betray us, we would tell him what we had done; but we would not have the <hi>Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards</hi> to know it, leſt they ſhould take them from us; The which he promis'd but broke it; and would fain have had two or three of them, to have brought them for <hi>England;</hi> but we ſaw his end: And when he ſaw he could not prevail, he ſaid they were worth two or three hundred pieces of eight a piece; Whereat both the Maſter and I told him, if they would give many Thouſands, they ſhould not have one, for we hoped to ſend them home again.</p>
            <p>So he looked upon us as Fools, becauſe we would not ſell them; the which I would not have done for the whole Iſland. But contrary to our expectations, he told the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> who threatned to take them from us: but ſo ſoon as we heard thereof, we called out all the <hi>Turks,</hi> and told them they muſt help us, for the <hi>Spaniards</hi> would take them from us. So they reſolvedly helped us, and we made all haſte to run from the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> the which pleaſed the <hi>Turks</hi> very well. So we put our ſelves to the hazard of the <hi>Turks,</hi> and being taken again, to ſave them</p>
            <p>So we continued about ſix or ſeven days, not being willing to put into any Port of <hi>Spain,</hi> for fear of loſing of the <hi>Turks.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We let them have all their liberty for four days, till they made an attempt to riſe, the which I foreſaw, and prevented
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:45513:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>without any harm: I was very Courteous to them, at the which ſome of our men grumbled; ſaying, <hi>I had more Care of the Turks than them:</hi> My Anſwer was, <hi>They are Strangers, I muſt treat them well.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At laſt, I told the Maſter it might do well to go to the <hi>Turks</hi> Coaſt, for there it was more likely to miſs their Men of War than where we were; and alſo it might fall out ſo, that we might have an opportunity to put the <hi>Turks</hi> on Shoar: To which the Maſter agreed.</p>
            <p>And in two days we were near the <hi>Turks</hi> Shore at a place called <hi>Cape hone,</hi> about Fifty Miles from <hi>Argier,</hi> as the <hi>Turks</hi> told us. So when we came about ſix miles from the Shore, it fell calm, and I had very much working in my mind, about getting them aſhore.</p>
            <p>At laſt I went to the Maſter and told him, I had a great deſire to put the <hi>Turks</hi> on Shore, but how I knew not; for to give them the Boat, they might go and get Men and Arms, and ſo take us again; and to put half on Shoar, they would raiſe the Country and ſurpriſe us when we came with the reſt. But if he would let me go, and if three more would go with me, I would venture to put them on Shoar; to which he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented.</p>
            <p>So then I ſpoke to the men, and there were two more, and my ſelf and a Boy took in the 10 <hi>Turks</hi> all looſe, and went a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout ſix miles and put them on Shore in their own Countrey, within about four miles of two Towns which they knew. With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al we gave them about fifty Padas of Bread and other neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries to Travel with. They would fain have enticed us to go to the Towns, telling us we ſhould have Wines, and many other things: as to their parts, I could have ventured with them. They all embraced me very kindly in their Arms when they went aſhore. They made one Riſing in the Boat when going aſhore, the which I prevented; and we parted with a great deal of love.</p>
            <p>When we came home to <hi>England,</hi> the King came to the Veſſels ſide, and enquired an Account, the which the Maſter gave him.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:45513:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>So this is as near as I can certifie thee; I have writ thee more atlarge to give thee the whole as it was; but thou mayſt take what is the moſt material; and ſo I reſt thine in that which can do good for evil, which ought to be the practice of all true men.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thomas Lurting.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Liverpoole,</hi> 
                  <date>the 30 of the fifth month, 1680.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:45513:12"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
